<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>fqsss - education</title>
    <subtitle>my obscure personal site as physics student + machine dictactor</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://firman-qs.github.io/tags/education/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://firman-qs.github.io/"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://firman-qs.github.io/tags/education/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>What We Teach, What We License, and What We Ignore</title>
        <published>2025-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://firman-qs.github.io/education/moving-to-oss/"/>
        <id>https://firman-qs.github.io/education/moving-to-oss/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://firman-qs.github.io/education/moving-to-oss/">&lt;p&gt;Most of us have experienced this since our school days. From an early age, we
are taught to use proprietary software: Microsoft Office, Adobe products,
Windows. Later, at university, the list grows longer—SPSS, MATLAB, Delphi, and
many others. In an ideal situation, this wouldn’t be a problem. If students are
financially able to buy the software, or if schools and universities provide
proper student licenses, everything works as intended. That’s great. But what if
they don’t?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When licenses are not provided, an uncomfortable reality appears: &lt;em&gt;piracy&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The
situation becomes even worse when teachers or lecturers require students to use
specific proprietary software without offering any legal access to it. In a
research methodology course, we were taught using SPSS. In scientific computing,
we were taught MATLAB (or similar tools). In principle, this is fine. Software
is just a medium. Ideally, students are first taught the underlying theory, and
the software merely helps automate calculations that would otherwise be tedious
and error-prone. MATLAB, for example, also makes visualization much more
convenient. The real problem starts when exams or assignments require
submissions in a specific proprietary format, while the university provides no
license at all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, many universities do provide licenses—&lt;em&gt;but not all&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Sometimes
students rely on free trials, which act as a temporary escape hatch. But even
then, another issue remains: students are trained exclusively on one specific
software ecosystem. Not all students have the time, resources, or background to
independently learn alternative tools outside the classroom—especially in
developing countries. When educational institutions fail to provide licenses,
students are left with only two options: &lt;em&gt;buy the software themselves (buying
can also be done illegally), or crack it&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The latter is clearly undesirable,
yet it is a well-known and often normalized practice in certain societies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this situation particularly ironic is that instructors often loudly
emphasize &lt;em&gt;“avoid plagiarism”, while quietly turning away from software piracy&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.
I try to give them the benefit of the doubt—perhaps they simply don’t realize
the contradiction. Many of them are not software engineers or creators, so they
may not directly feel the impact.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Still, that doesn’t make it right.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-foss&quot;&gt;The FOSS&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, no shortage of free and open-source software out there.
This naturally raises a simple question: &lt;em&gt;why don’t we use them?&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; The simplest
answer is also the most honest one—&lt;em&gt;we are trained from a very young age&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to use
proprietary software. From childhood, we are introduced to Windows. When we
learn to write documents, create presentations, or manage spreadsheets, we are
taught Microsoft Office. When we work with vector graphics, we are taught Corel
or Adobe. For bitmap image processing, Adobe again. Social science students
learn statistics through SPSS; qualitative research introduces NVivo; scientific
research relies on OriginPro, MATLAB, and so on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine a &lt;em&gt;different default&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: the laptops we bought came with Linux and
LibreOffice preinstalled. Of course, LibreOffice may not feel as convenient as
Microsoft Office for advanced academic writing—but then again, there is
$\LaTeX$. I’m not saying we should teach $\LaTeX$ to elementary or high school
students—that would be extreme. At that level, open-source office tools are more
than sufficient, especially since students are not yet producing long or complex
documents. Once students reach university, however, LaTeX becomes a very
reasonable option.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For vector graphics, we have Inkscape. For bitmap editing, GIMP. For 3D
modeling, Blender. For statistics and programming—both beginner-friendly and
advanced—we have Python, paired with the beautifully expressive Jupyter
Notebook. Personally, I believe that translating statistical theory into lines
of code—rather than clicking through menus—leads to deeper, more meaningful
learning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this makes one thing very clear: the opportunity to use open-source
alternatives is wide open. The real question is, whether we are willing to be
open to them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, students should not be entirely dependent on what is taught in
schools or universities. They must learn independently. In my opinion, the best
way to learn is self-learning. &lt;em&gt;Stop immediately asking questions&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;—of course, ask
when you truly need urgent clarification—but &lt;em&gt;try first to think, search, reason,
answer, and verify things yourself&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, sometimes instructors say, &lt;em&gt;“This is not our field, so I won’t go too far into
it.”&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Unfortunately, this is often misunderstood by students as &lt;em&gt;“I don’t need to
learn anything outside my major.”&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I strongly disagree. We should learn across
disciplines—or at least those closely connected to our field—as much as
possible, even if not deeply. Multidisciplinary knowledge is no longer optional;
it is a necessity, alongside having one or two core specializations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this last point, I actually have more to say. The issue is interesting
enough that I plan to write about it in a future post.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a small but important note: I am not saying that proprietary software
is bad. On the contrary, there are clear reasons why Windows, Microsoft Office,
Adobe, and similar tools are so popular. Beyond being widely taught, they are
genuinely comfortable and polished products. And that very comfort—the ease they
provide—is precisely what made them dominant in the first place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
